Ira V. Hiscock collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Ira V. Hiscock collection
1914-1987
1930-1973
Ms Coll 45
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
5
(9 boxes)
The collection contains public health surveys by Hiscock and others; some correspondence; materials related to Hiscock's activities in Yale-in-China and the World Health Assembly; materials on Hiscock's awards; photographs and memorabilia on the dedication of the Ira V. Hiscock Library; and memorabilia that were to be assembled in scrapbooks, especially from the period after his retirement.
Hiscock, Ira V. (Ira Vaughan), 1892-
Custodial History
Donated to the Epidemiology and Public Health (EPH) Library by Margaret Hiscock Weatherly, Mount Laurel, N.J. Transferred to the Medical Historical Library, 2013.
Related Materials
Related archival materials at Yale include Ira V. Hiscock scrapbook, Manuscript 20th cent, and Ira V. Hiscock scrapbook of articles relating to his career, Manuscript 20th cent, both in the Medical Historical Library; and Ira Vaughan Hiscock Papers (MS 1284), Manuscripts and Archives. The Medical Historical Library has a bound set of Hiscock's articles.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Yale does not own copyright.
Biographical / Historical
Ira V. Hiscock received a master's in public health from Yale in 1921 and served on the faculty of the Department of Public Health from 1920 on. He attained the rank of full professor in 1931 and became chairman of the department and Anna M. R. Lauder Professor in 1947, serving until his retirement in 1960. He was active in a large number of organizations and especially known for his work directing health surveys and in strengthening community public health organizations.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: 1. Health surveys and related materials. 2. Other Hiscock materials. 3. Supplement, 2016.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains public health surveys, mostly in mimeograph form, by Hiscock, as well as related surveys collected by Hiscock; speeches; some correspondence; materials related to Hiscock's work as a trustee of the Yale-in-China Association; materials related to his role as a member of the U.S. delegation to the World Health Assembly in 1958, and materials that were to be assembled in scrapbooks, especially from the period after his retirement. The supplement includes, among other items, correspondence of Philip E. Nelbach on public health in Westport; clippings on a community survey of the Greater Hartford area in 1948; mimeographs on polio in Connecticut ca. 1959; materials on Hiscock's awards; correspondence of Hiscock after his retirement with Edward R. DeLouise, Director of Public Health in New Haven; and photographs from the dedication of the Ira V. Hiscock Library (former EPH Library).
Epidemiology -- United States; Health surveys -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Health surveys -- Maryland -- Baltimore; Health surveys -- Hawaii; Health surveys -- New York (State) -- New York; Health surveys -- Ohio -- Dayton; Health surveys -- Ohio -- Montgomery County; Health surveys -- Ohio -- Stark County; Health surveys -- Mississippi -- Pike County; Health surveys -- Tennessee -- Rutherford County; Health surveys -- Tennessee -- Sullivan County; Health surveys -- Washington (D.C.); Hospitals -- Washington (D.C.); Poliomyelitis -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 1955-1960; Public health administration; Public health -- Education -- Hawaii; Public health -- Education -- Tennessee; Public health -- Connecticut -- Westport; School health services -- Taiwan; World War, 1939-1945 -- Health aspects; Clippings; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Health educators -- United States; Bishop, E. L. (Eugene Lindsay), 1886-; DeLouise, Edward R. (Edward Rocco); Dublin, Thomas D.; Falk, I. S. (Isidore Sydney), 1899-1984; Hiscock, Ira V. (Ira Vaughan), 1892-; Munger, Claude W. (Claude Worrell), 1892-1950; Nelbach, Philip Edward, 1913-; Nyswander, Dorothy B. (Dorothy Bird), 1894-1998; Park, Edwards A. (Edwards Albert), 1877-1969; Payne, A. M.-M; Scamman, Clarence Linwood, 1888-; Walker, W. Frank (Watson Frank), 1889?-1941; Winslow, C.-E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1877-1957; American Public Health Association; Commonwealth Foundation; Connecticut Public Health Association; Connecticut State Medical Society; East Harlem Health Center; Greenwich Hospital (Greenwich, Conn.); Milbank Memorial Fund; National Society for the Prevention of Blindness; New England Public Health Association; Oahu Health Council; Tennessee Valley Authority. Health and Safety Department; World Health Organization; Yale-in-China Association; Yale University. Department of Epidemiology and Public Health; Yale University. Department of Public Health; Yale University. School of Public Health -- History; White House Conference on Child Health and Protection; World Health Assembly (11th) -- Minneapolis -- 1958
- Health surveys and related materials, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Hiscock was asked to head or consult on many health surveys of cities, counties, and states across the United States. These reports contained data on mortality and morbidity, and examined the accomplishments and effectiveness of the various local organizations and institutions that served the health of the public. Some of the surveys in this series are by Hiscock. Others are related surveys that he collected. Many of the surveys were sponsored by such organizations as the Milbank Memorial Fund, the Commonwealth Fund, or the American Public Health Association. See also surveys in Box 8.
  - Hawaii
    - Hawaii population statistics for 1910 and 1920, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "The Medical Care and Protection of Children in the Territory of Hawaii", 1932-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Typescript of presentation from the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, Medical Service Section, as prepared for publication. 94 numbered leaves plus maps.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "A Survey of Public Health Activities in Honolulu, Hawaii: Includes Official and Voluntary Agencies, Under the Auspices of the Chamber of Commerce", 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Carbon of typescript, 227 pages. "With the cooperation of the Committee of Administrative Practice of the American Public Health Association."
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "Public Health in Military Government in Hawaii", November 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Carbon of typescript, 51 leaves, including some printed pages. "For Part II of Volume of the Surgeon General on History of Preventive Medicine in World War II..." Hiscock was the author of Public Health in Hawaii. Report of health survey in 1950 ... under the auspices of the Oahu health council, inc., with the cooperation of the Board of health, Territory of Hawaii, and Survey advisory groups on Hawaii, Kauai, Maui, Molokai and Oahu [Honolulu, 1950].
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "Public Health in Honolulu: Report of a Health Inventory", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      74 mimeographed leaves. Report undertaken "under the auspices of the Oahu Health Council, Inc." Hiscock, having retired from Yale in 1960, was Carnegie Visiting Professor of Public Health, University of Hawaii in 1960.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, Draft public health inventories of the Big Island, Kauai, Lanai, Maui, and Molokai, 1960 September (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "Public Health in Hawaii: Report of a Health Inventory in 1960" (Box 1, Folder 7)
      51 mimeographed leaves. Conducted "under the auspices of the Oahu Health Council."
    - Other materials related to Hiscock and Hawaii, 1950, 1960; 1960-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hiscock Lectures, University of Hawaii, 1963, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Ira V. Hiscock Annual Lectureship, University of Hawaii, presented by Ira V. Hiscock, 1963 (including a long introduction by the President of the Oahu Health Council on Hiscock's accomplishments); Ira V. Hiscock Lecture, University of Hawaii, 1982, presented by Dorothy Nyswander.
  - Tennessee Valley Authority
    - "Health Education Project, University of Tennessee", ca. 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Carbon of typescript. No indication of author.
    - Robert H. White, et al, "Public Health Education Program: Report on Progress and Plans, Submitted to the Planning Committee, June 22, 1936", 1936 June 22; Mimeographed typescript, 36 leaves. Mention is made on p. 34 of Ira Hiscock who was hired as Public Health Education Consultant in 1934, and on p, 35 of Dr. H. H. Walker, from the Department of Public Health at Yale, who was made available to teach public health education at the University of Tennessee. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Robert H. White and H. H. Walker, "Report to the State Planning Committee on the Public Health Education Program in Tennessee", 1937 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Mimeographed typescript. Various paginations.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "The Tennessee Plan of Health Education", 1938 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Carbon of typed manuscript, 26 leaves.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "A Study of the Program of Health Education of the Tennessee Valley Authority", 1941 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Mimeographed typescript, 15 pages.
    - H. L. Case, "Proposed Program in Health Education for 1941-42", 1941 July 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Carbon copy.
    - "A Proposed Nutrition Education Program for Employees of the Tennessee Valley Authority", 1941 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Carbon copy of a typescript,12 leaves. No indication of author.
    - W. F. Walker and C. L. Scamman, "Appraisal of Health Activities in Pike County, Mississippi, for the Year 1931", 1932 April (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - W. F. Walker and H. E. Handley, "Study and Appraisal of Health Activities, Pike County, Mississippi, 1932", 1933 April (Box 2, Folder 4)
      This and other health reports are mimeographed typescripts. The research was sponsored by the Commonwealth Fund. W. F. Walker, D.P.H., was a member of the Division of Research Studies of the Commonwealth Fund.
    - W. F. Walker, "Survey of Health Activities in Pike County, Mississippi for the Year 1933", 1934 March (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - W. F. Walker, "Survey of Health Activities in Pike County, Mississippi for the Year 1934", 1935 March (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - W. F. Walker, "Survey of Health Activities in Pike County, Mississippi, for the Year 1935", 1936 March (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - W. F. Walker, "A Study of Public Health Activities in Rutherford County, Tennessee for the Year 1926", 1927 February 19-25 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Mimeographed typescript, 27 leaves. By the Committee on Administrative Practice, American Public Health Association.
    - W. F. Walker and Clarence Scamman, "Summary and Appraisal of Health Activities in Rutherford County, Tennessee, for the Year 1931", 1932 April (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Issued by the Commonwealth Fund. Mimeographed typescript, 28 leaves.
    - "Survey and Appraisal of Health Activities, Rutherford County, Tennessee for the Year 1932", ca. 1933 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Mimeographed typescript similar to others in this subseries, 60 leaves. No author or sponsor stated.
    - W. F. Walker and Clarence L. Scamman, "Survey of Health Activities, Sullivan County, Tennessee, for the Year 1931", 1932 April (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Issued by the Commonwealth Fund. Mimeographed typescript, 34 leaves.
    - "Summary and Appraisal of Health Activities of Sullivan County, Tennessee, for the Year 1932", 1933 May (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Issued by the Commonwealth Fund. Mimeographed typescript, 68 leaves.
    - W. F. Walker, "Survey of Health Activities in Sullivan County, Tennessee, for the Year 1933", 1934 April (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Issued by the Commonwealth Fund. Mimeographed typescript, 46 leaves.
    - W. F. Walker, "Survey of Health Activities in Sullivan County, Tennessee, for the Year 1934", 1935 April (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Issued by the Commonwealth Fund. Mimeographed typescript, 36 leaves
    - W. F. Walker, "Survey of Health Activities in Sullivan County, Tennessee, for the Year 1935", 1936 May (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Issued by the Commonwealth Fund. Mimeographed typescript, 35 leaves.
    - "Malaria in Our Community: A Study of a Malaria Education Study in an Elementary School", 1941 October (Box 2, Folder 16)
      By the Tennessee Valley Authority. Introduction by E. L. Bishop, M.D., Director of Health, Tennessee Valley Authority. The report was written by teachers participating in the project in a school in rural north Alabama. Mimeographed typescript, 14 leaves.
    - H. A. Morgan, "The Tennessee Valley Authority's Contribution to National Coordination--Agricultural and Land Use Phase", 1934 November 27 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Mimeographed typescript, 11 leaves. Text marked up and additional handwritten notes on lined paper, presumably by Ira Hiscock. Included is a handwritten note from E. L. Bishop to Hiscock asking for his comments.
  - Ohio
    - W. F. Walker, Carl E. Buck, Ira V. Hiscock, and Homer N. Calver, Report of a Study of the Ohio Public Health Association, 1931 June (Box 3, Folder 1)
      "For the Committee on Administrative Practices." Mimeographed typescript, various paginations, published by the American Public Health Association. Inserted is a loose carbon of a letter from Howard W. Green to W. W. Charters, Bureau of Educational Research, Ohio State University, commenting on the report.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, James A. Hamilton, Albert L. Burgdorf, et al., Part I - Public Health: Health and Hospital Study of Dayton and Montgomery County, 1946 June (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Conducted under the auspices of the Chamber of Commerce, the Community Chest Association, the Metropolitan Health Council, Montgomery County Medical Society, and the Citizens Sponsoring Committee. Mimeographed typescript, 84 leaves.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, James A. Hamilton, Albert L. Burgdorf, et al, Public Health in Dayton and Montgomery County: Report of a Health and Hospital Study, 1946 June 28 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      "Conducted under the auspices of the Citizens Sponsoring Committee for Health and Hospital Study of Dayton and Montgomery County, Ohio." Carbon of a typescript, 134 leaves.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, et al., Public Health in Stark County, Ohio: A Survey of Public Health in Alliance, Canton, Massillon and Stark County, Ohio, ca. 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      "Conducted under the auspices of the county Survey Committee for the Year 1947 by staff representatives of Community Surveys Associated, New York." "Work copy - not for publication." Mimeographed typescript, 133 leaves. Photostat charts are loosely inserted on mortality from tuberculosis, infant mortality, mortality from cancer and other malignant tumors, mortality from diarrhea and enteritis, puerperal mortality, mortality from chronic diseases, mortality from diabetes, mortality from pneumonia, and mortality from all causes. All of these charts are for the years 1944-1946.
    - Pamphlets, articles, and reports related to the Cleveland Health Museum, 1953-1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Hiscock appears to have collected these.
  - Metropolitan Washington, D.C.
    - Ira V. Hiscock, [Health Survey of Washington, D.C.]: "Part I. Public Health Activities in Washington, D.C." "Part II. Community Relationships of Hospitals", ca. 1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Charles F. Neergaard, "Program for Expansion of Hospital Facilities in the Metropolitan Area of Washington, D.C", 1941 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Metropolitan Health and Hospital Survey": Remarks of C.-E. A. Winslow and of Claude V. Munger, 1946 May 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Mimeographed typescripts plus handwritten drafts of Winslow's remarks and of his introduction to the survey. The survey was distributed in mimeographed form as Council of Social Agencies of the District of Columbia and Vicinity, Health and Hospital Survey of Metropolitan Washington, including District of Columbia, Alexandria, Va., Fairfax County, Va., Arlington County, Va., Montgomery County, Md., Prince George's County, Md., by C.-E. A. Winslow, Ira V. Hiscock, and Claude W. Munger, 1946. A copy of the survey has been cataloged separately and is in the Historical Library.
    - Supplementary material for the Health and Hospital Survey of Metropolitan Washington, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      See notes to previous folder for citation to the survey. Includes mimeographed "Supplement," August 1947, and "Limited Index," 1948.
  - Baltimore
    - Ira V. Hiscock, James Hamilton, Hugh Leavell, and Ella L. Pensinger, "Survey of the Medical Care Advances of the Community Fund of Baltimore", 1940 February - April (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Carbon copy typescript, 178 leaves, plus loose tables. This is likely a draft.
    - Ira V. Hiscock correspondence with Edwards A. Park concerning the Baltimore survey, 1940 May (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Edwards A. Park was a pediatrician at Johns Hopkins University. He had chaired the Department of Pediatrics at Yale from 1922 to 1927.
  - New York City
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "District Health Administration: A Study of Organization and Planning", ca. 1936 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Carbon typescript in a binder, various pagination. Foreward by John L. Rice, M.D., Commissioner of Health, New York City. The next folder has related loose material
    - Ira V. Hiscock, "District Health Administration: A Study of Organization and Planning," additional material, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Additional chapters that go with the previous folder. Included is a letter from Victor Freeburg, Milbank Memorial Fund, to Hiscock, April 14, 1936, on the publication of the manuscript.
    - Reports on East Harlem health services, 1927-1931 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      "The Maternity Service in the General Health Program," 1927; "Report of the Morbidity Service," ca. 1928; and "East Harlem Health Center," 1931. The latter includes a charts photographs of the outside of the health center. These reports are not by Hiscock.
  - Other health surveys, 1919-1933 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Jeanette Bullis, "Public Health Study, Glen Cove, Long Island", 1919 April 28
    - Philip S. Platt and Annette N. Platt, "A Health Survey and Appraisal of Orlando, Florida", 1926 March 15 - 1926 April 7
    - S. A. Douglass, "What Has Been Learned Concerning the Prevention and Control of Tuberculosis in a Rural County from Five Years of Health Demonstration Work in Cattaraugus [NY]", ca. 1928
    - W. L. Halverson, "Diphtheria Control in Los Angeles County", ca. 1933
- Other Hiscock materials, Series II
  - Yale-in-China Association Trustees, 1959, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Ira Hiscock served as a trustee of the Yale-in-China Association from 1959 to 1972. Most of the material in the folder dates from 1971-1972. Contents include minutes, drafts of speeches, some correspondence, photographs of Hiscock's visit(s) to China, and reports on the new health services of the Chinese University of Hong Kong. Hiscock served as Chairman of Advisory Health Committee of Yale-in-China in 1972. Of interest is Hiscock's "confidential' draft, June 18, 1959, on trying to restart Yale-in-China after the Communist takeover by working with the New Asia College, which eventually became part of the Chinese University of Hong Kong.
  - United States Delegation to the Tenth Anniversary Commemorative Session of the World Health Organization and the Eleventh World Health Assembly, Minneapolis, 1958 May 24-29 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Hiscock was a member of the American Delegation to the Tenth Anniversary Commemorative Session of the World Health Organization, held in Minneapolis Minnesota, May 26-28. This was followed by the Eleventh World Health Assembly, also in Minneapolis, May 28-June 14. Hiscock attended only through May 29. The folder contains handouts for members of the American Delegation and invitations to Hiscock to attend associated events.
  - Materials on The Tenth Anniversary of W.H.O., 1958 May 24-28 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    The session took place on May 26-28, 1958. Included are an address by the President of the Assembly and speeches by the chief delegates of a number of countries.
  - W.H.O. materials, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Pamphlets and mimeographed information about W.H.O. distributed at the Assembly.
  - Materials related to Hiscock's courses at Yale, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Class Seminar Questions 1958" [on W.H.O.]
    - Thomas D. Dublin, "Looking Ahead in Epidemiology," Concluding Lecture, Survey Course in Epidemiology, 1958 January 31
      Mimeographed typescript, 39 leaves, of invited lecture for Hiscock's Survey Course in Epidemiology (PH 101).
    - A. M.-M. Payne, "Global Epidemiology Today," presented in Symposium, Perspectives in Epidemiology, Yale University, 1959 February 20
  - "The Life and Age of Man, edited by Ira Vaughan Hiscock", 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Typescript, 3 leaves, on stages of life. This piece relates to the Centennial of the American Public Health Association.
  - Clippings on Hiscock's retirement and the appointment of his successor, 1959 December 6 - 1959 December 7 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Hiscock retired as of January 1, 1960 and Anthony Monck-Mason Payne was appointed Anna M. R. Lauder Professor and Chairman of the reorganized Department of Epidemiology and Public Health.
  - Ira V. Hiscock Lecture, Yale University, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Invitation, program and published version of the first Ira V. Hiscock Lecture at Yale, presented by Leona Baumgartner, 1966. Her presentation was "But What About the People," American Journal of Public Health 57(1967): 610-617.
  - Presentations by C.-E. A. Winslow, 1926, 1940-1948 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Presentations by others, 1914, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Copies of typescripts: Herman Biggs, "Famous Epidemics: Data in Regard to Certain Important Epidemics. For Illustrative Use in Connection with Lectures upon Public Health," ca. 1914; and Dorothy B. Nyswander, "Education for Health - Some Principles and Their Applications," 1956. These were possibly used in courses.
  - Hiscock scrapbook materials, 1945-1973 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Incoming letters and other materials taped into a notebook along with loose material added. The majority of the items are dated 1973. There is material on Isidore S. Falk being awarded the Sedgwick Memorial Medal from the American Association of Public Health in 1973. Also of note are a draft of a speech by Hiscock, "Case Study of Voluntarism, as Illustrated by the National Society for Prevention of Blindness," February 15, 1973.
  - Hiscock scrapbook materials, 1922-1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Similar to the previous file. Contains incoming letters, programs, photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia. Of significance are a draft of a speech by Hiscock, "The New England Public Health Association of 1970: Highlights, Gaps, Bridges, and Ambitions," May 25, 1970; and a photocopy of a presentation by Hiscock, "The Setting and the Seal," New England Public Health Association, May 22-24, 1968. Most materials are from the 1970s.
  - Hiscock's Awards
    All the paper-based awards were framed. The frames have been removed for archival storage.
    - Yale University Hospital Administration Alumni Association, ca. 1960 (Box 6)
      Metal plaque mounted on wood.
    - "To Ira V. Hiscock and the Faculty of Yale School of Public Health", 1953-1954
      Metal plate attached to a wooden backing. From ten named individuals (seven M.D.s) from foreign countries.
    - Honorary Degree in Medicine from the Connecticut State Medical Society, 1973 December 13 (Box 7)
    - "Citation for Service to the World's Health", 1972 January
      From the American Association for World Health, Inc. and U.S. Committee for the World Health Organization.